Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series VI. Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention
1967-1968
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.06
8.75 Linear Feet
Governor Raymond P. Shafer made constitutional reform a priority and voters were asked in the May 1967 primary to call a limited Constitutional Convention (Con Con). Dick Thornburgh's successful campaign for delegate and subsequent participation at the Constitutional Convention are well documented here. The four areas for which constitutional amendments were considered were: finance and taxation, the judiciary, legislative reapportionment, and local government. Thornburgh has continued to be an active proponent of merit-selection and home rule. The files are in twelve sections: Background reports and articles; Campaign for and delegate to Con Con; Convention opening and procedures; Convention Committees; Judiciary Committee working files; Judiciary Committee Subcommittees; Delegate Thornburgh's Files; Clippings, Editorials and Bulletins; Home Rule; Efforts to Implement Judiciary Article; Thornburgh's working copies of manuals, proposals and hearings; and Hardcover publications of Con Con. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Judges -- Selection and appointment -- United States; Home rule -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Personal papers; Government; Politics; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania. Constitutional Convention (1967-1968); Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Thornburgh, Dick; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Home Rule Charter Advisory Committee
- Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention, 1967-1968; VI.
  Scope and Contents note
  Following rather close on the heels of the '66 campaign for U.S. Congress, yet another Thornburgh campaign got underway despite some advice from friends to the contrary. Newly elected Pennsylvania Governor Raymond P. Shafer made constitutional reform a priority for his administration and voters were asked in the May 1967 primary to call a limited Constitutional Convention. Thornburgh's long standing interest in judicial reform and his then developing concerns about local government tempted him to run in his own Forty-third District, although heavily Democratic. Thornburgh's successful campaign for delegate and subsequent participation at the Constitutional Convention are well documented here as well as the workings of the convention, which the press quickly dubbed "Con Con." To date this remains Pennsylvania's most recent Constitutional Convention.
  There were four specific areas for which constitutional amendments were to be considered: finance and taxation, the judiciary, legislative reapportionment, and local government. The Convention opened on December 1, 1967 and continued for three months during which time Thornburgh commuted back and forth between Pittsburgh and Harrisburg. Following the convention's closing on February 28, 1968, he participated in efforts to enact the resultant four proposals in the May 6 primary, particularly the judicial article, and embarked on a vigorous speaking tour to solicit voter support. Although all four were successfully passed in the primary, unfortunately the next year the watered-down judicial merit selection plan was defeated in a separate referendum. Thornburgh has continued to date to be an active proponent of merit-selection as evidenced in ongoing articles and op-eds (available here online).
  Home Rule is a topic somewhat surprisingly very well documented here, a topic with which Thornburgh has maintained continuous interest up to and including the passage in 1998 of Pittsburgh's home rule charter. His 1969 article "Blueprint for Modern Government: A Home Rule Charter for Pittsburgh" is a "package of recommendations - some of which, years, later, were actually included in the Pittsburgh charter - [which] received a good deal of publicity and editorial approval" (Evidence, p. 36).
  "All of us who participated in this historic gathering took great satisfaction in our accomplishments ... For me, it was a truly exhilarating experience. After years of only talking about the political process, I had finally been able to be a central participant in the 'nuts and bolts' of a significant government effort ... I arrived home ... anxious to seek out the next challenge" ("Evidence" draft, p. 126).
  The files are in twelve sections: "Background reports and articles," "Campaign for and delegate to Con Con," "Convention opening and procedures," "Convention Committees," "Judiciary Committee working files," "Judiciary Committee Subcommittees," "Delegate Thornburgh's Files," "Clippings, Editorials and Bulletins," "Home Rule," "Efforts to Implement Judiciary Article," "Thornburgh's working copies of manuals, proposals and hearings," and "Hardcover publications of Con Con."
  - Background Reports and Articles, 1.
    These records include background reports regarding constitutional revision in Pennsylvania over the years 1959-1967. There also are reports and drafts prepared by the Pennsylvania Bar Association and National Municipal League on subjects to be considered at the convention. The Pennsylvania Senate Bill "providing for a constitutional convention" is included as well as articles about judicial reform and other relevant constitutional issues.
    - Background Reports and Booklets Regarding Constitutional Revision in Pennsylvania, 1959-1967 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Major reports and drafts submitted by PA Bar Assn (annotated), and National Municipal League, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - State Constitutional Reform and Home Rule issues and background accompanying draft of paper entitled "The State Constitution as Symbol and as Instrument" by Harry Woodruff Turner, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - PA Senate Bill No. 1 "providing for a constitutional convention", 1967 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - "Proposals of the Pennsylvania Bar Association" and Statement regarding proposed Judiciary Article, July 31, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - "Judicial Reform in Pennsylvania" by Mercer D. Tate -Reprinted from Villanova Law Review Vol. 10, No. 2 (Winter 1965) (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - "Proceedings of the Seminar On Constitutional Issues" (annotated): Council for a More Effective Constitutional Convention," Penn State University, October 6, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Campaign for and Delegate to the Constitutional Convention, 2.
    In typical fashion, Dick Thornburgh meticulously maintained records both of his campaign and his participation at the convention. Much of the material is annotated and many drafts of proposals and articles are included. The news releases from his delegate campaign are particularly interesting background on the prospective work and goals of the convention and are available here online. His delegate news releases (also available online) and mailings further document the ongoing news from the convention. Delegate lists, programs and ephemera are here as well as the "Convention Reporter" news bulletins. Although convention proposals no doubt are available elsewhere, Thornburgh's individual delegate participation and personal delegate records from the convention in progress appear to be unique and especially of interest.
    - Delegate Campaign
      - Better Constitution Committee, Thornburgh Chairman and Treasurer, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Delegate Campaign: memos, correspondence, clippings, editorials, brochures and drafts, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - Campaign News Releases, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 10)
        - Thornburgh Says Democrats Show "Contempt" for Charter Reform, August 27, 1967; 1.
        - Thornburgh Charges Mazzei with "Power Grab", September 3, 1967; 2.
        - Thornburgh Chides Moorhead for Poverty Politics, September, 1967; 3.
        - No one is Closer to Operation of Law Among Ordinary Citizens than Lawyers Who Serve with Anti-Poverty Program's Neighborhood Legal Services Association, October 4, 1967; 4.
        - Thornburgh to Attend Seminar on Constitutional Issues, October, 1967; 5.
        - Democratic Charter Candidates "Unfit," Thornburgh Says, October, 1967; 6.
        - Minor Judiciary Poll Results "Shocking," Thornburgh Says, October 19, 1967; 7.
        - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County Citizens Should be Shocked by Results of Poll Concerning Operation of the Minor Judiciary, 1967; 8.
        - Debate Challenge Renewed by Doyle and Thornburgh, 1967; 9.
        - Thornburgh, Doyle Propose Charter Revision Debates, 1967; 10.
        - Scranton Warned of Opposition to Judicial Reform, 1967; 11.
        - Mazzei Blocks Constitutional Debate, Thornburgh Charges, 1967; 12.
        - Constitution Needs Minor Judiciary "New Look," Thornburgh Says, 1967; 13.
        - Thornburgh Hits Moorhead's 1967 Record, 14.
        - Thornburgh's Statement for Radio Station WTAE, 1967; 15.
        - Thornburgh Lauds Home Rule Proposals, 1967; 16.
      - Con Con Clips and Editorials re: Delegate Campaigns, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 11)
      - Letters of Congratulations on Election as Delegate to the Convention, August -December 1967 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Delegate to Con Con
      - Delegate News Releases and Mailings, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 13)
        - Thornburgh's proposal paves way for elimination of antiquated elective office of coroner in Pennsylvania, December 20, 1967; 1.
        - Thornburgh discloses that Mazzei wife on Public Rolls, February 7, 1968; 2.
        - Thornburgh hails 'People's Fight' against Minor Judiciary, February 8, 1968; 3.
        - Thornburgh hails Con Con Work; Hits "Nay-Sayers", March 5, 1968; 4.
        - Thornburgh asks Lawyers to Support Con Con Judiciary Proposal, March 13, 1968; 5.
        - Don't Break Faith on Minor Judiciary Reform, Thornburgh Asks, March 20, 1968; 6.
        - Thornburgh Asks Bar Association to Support Con Con Judiciary Proposal, March 22, 1968; 7.
        - Con Con Bi-Partisan Effort, Thornburgh Tells G.O.P. Women, March 27, 1968; 8.
        - Thornburgh Suggests Con Con Judiciary Objections are "Smokescreen", April 16, 1968; 9.
        - Thornburgh Labels Con Con Home Rule Objections "Red Herring", March 25, 1968; 10.
        - Con Con Proposals Speak to Ghetto Problems, Says Thornburgh, April 14, 1968; 11.
        - Appoint Charter Commission Now, Thornburgh Asks Mayor, April 25, 1968; 12.
        - Thornburgh scores Mazzei "Triple Dip" and asks Resignation, 1968; 13.
        - Thornburgh hits Fleming Criticism of Judiciary Article, 1968; 14.
        - Remarks of Richard L. Thornburgh, Delegate to Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention from the 43rd Senatorial District, 1968; 15.
        - Thornburgh Praises Con Con Delegates; Sees Healthy Compromises, 1968; 16.
        - Con Con Judiciary Article Objections Termed "Misinformed", 1968; 17.
        - Con Con Judiciary Article Objections "Unfounded," Thornburgh Says, 1968; 18.
      - Delegate to Con Con: programs, delegate ephemera, programs, expenses and events, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 14)
      - Delegate Binder: includes guidebook, roster, and daily "Convention Reporter" news bulletins, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 15)
      - Delegates to Con Con: Lists, directories, and license plate, undated (Box 26, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence from Thornburgh, Delegate, November 1967-April 1968 (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence to Thornburgh, Delegate, December 1967-December 1968 (Box 26, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence from Hymen Diamond, December 1967-March 1968 (Box 26, Folder 19)
      - Delegate Mail/Memos from Outside Organizations, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - Convention Opening and Procedures, 3.
    Opening remarks of Pennsylvania Governors Scranton and Shafer and President Broderick of the convention are included here. Thornburgh's early participation on the Temporary Committee on Rules and Organization is documented as well as his memo on proposed convention rules and procedures, much of which was taken into account in the final rules. One of his two committee appointments, here the Committee on Style and Drafting, contains agendas, drafts and edited convention proposals. "Counsels" to the convention are here, too. News releases and memoranda of the convention further document the convention in progress.
    - Opening of Con Con: Remarks by former Governor Scranton and Governor Shafer, December 1, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - President Broderick Remarks and Letters, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Temporary Committee on Rules and Organization; Thornburgh Memo: Suggested Proposed Convention Rules and Procedure (annotated), 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Committee on Style and Drafting: memos, agendas, drafts and edited convention proposals; Thornburgh a member, January-February 1968 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Counsel to Convention Opinions: Marvin Comisky (incomplete), 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - News releases and memoranda, January-March, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Convention Committees, 4.
    Materials from four major committees of the convention appear in this small section: local government, administrative and finance, legislative apportionment, and taxation and finance. These files include information from the public hearings before these committees, frequently with Thornburgh annotations. Additionally there is a report from the committee on "arrangement and submission and address to the people."
    - Local Government, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Administrative and Finance, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Legislative Apportionment, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - "Committee on Arrangement, Submission and Address to the People: Recommendation No. 1", 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Taxation and Finance, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Judiciary Committee Working Files, 5.
    Most of the early work of the convention was done in committee. Thornburgh was appointed to the Judiciary Committee where he served as Secretary. This rich group of files includes minutes, issues, drafts, memoranda, schedules, correspondence and proposals. There is much regarding Delegate Proposal 1000, the first proposed amendment to the constitution, which was submitted by Dick Thornburgh. This was the judicial reform plan drafted by the Pennsylvania Bar Association upon which he had worked for the previous five years. There is much here about the Judicial Committee Proposal 7 and rebutting objections to it. Attacks on the proposal focused on "merit selection" provisions designed to take judicial selection out of the political arena. The Judiciary Committee was co-chaired by former Governor Scranton and Philadelphia financier and community leader Gustave Amsterdam.
    - Minutes, Assignments and issues, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Drafts, Memoranda. Schedules and Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Action Reports, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Judiciary Proposal, drafts, January, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Judiciary Article, Amendments (annotated), February, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Delegate Proposal 1000, by RLT (annotated) later Judicial Proposal No.7, 1967-1968 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Judiciary Committee Proposal No. 7 Original and amended, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Endorsement of Proposal 1000 from Allegheny Bar Association: letter (Proposal 7), December 22, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Schedules to Supplement Proposal No. 7, February, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Judicial Committee Report in Support Of Committee Proposal No. 7 and Supporting correspondence, February, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Proposal No. 7: Pomeroy on behalf Of Allegheny County Bar Assn rebuts Objections to Proposal 7, April, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Judiciary Subcommittees, Correspondence and Issues, 6.
    A number of subcommittees worked on various aspects of judicial reform: minor judiciary, tenure, retirement, and selection of judges for example. These are essentially working files and include background information, drafts, proposals from subcommittees, and in some cases votes. Also here are files from the 1969 pre primary efforts to pass judicial reform proposals, more of which appear in section 06:10.
    - Judicial Issues
      - Judicial Issues in Philadelphia, January 1968 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Minor Judiciary Issues in Allegheny County, February, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Judicial Issues and Systems from Other States, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Articles and Reports
      - Correspondence to the Judiciary Committee, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Judicial Selection articles, reports and correspondence, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Pro/Con Judiciary speeches and article, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Subcommittees
      - Minor Judiciary, November-January, 1967-1968 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - Tenure, December 1967 (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Retirement, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Judicial Administration and Organization, Thornburgh Memo, undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Selection of Judges
      - Minutes and Proposals of Selection of Judges Sub Committee, December-January, 1967-1968 (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - Background Information, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 12)
      - Binder: drafts and proposals from subcommittees, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - Votes and Drafts, 1967-1968 (Box 28, Folder 14)
      - State and Local Judicial Nominating Commissions, December, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Pre Primary Actions regarding Merit Selection
      - Merit Selection-pre primary efforts to pass judicial reform proposals, April-May, 1969 (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - Thornburgh's Topic Files, 7.
    These topic files evidence Thornburgh's deep and ongoing interest in judicial and home rule topics. The materials consist of reports, articles and clippings and particularly in the case of "local government" (i.e. home rule) the files include relevant material dating prior to the convention. This material augments his actual working files of the convention.
    - The Courts, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Juvenile Courts, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Local Government, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Local and Municipal Taxation, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - County Taxation, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - State Taxation, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, Editorials and Bulletins, 8.
    This small group of material is in effect monitoring the public response to the actions and proposals of the convention in the form of news clippings and editorials during the months of the convention. Additionally there are bulletins from the convention itself, although not complete here.
    - Con Con original news clippings, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Con Con editorials, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - Con Con news bulletins (incomplete), 1968 (Box 28, Folder 25)
  - Home Rule, 9.
    These files document in detail Thornburgh's persistent interest in home rule, which was one of the two areas on which he concentrated at the convention. The local government amendment subsequently adopted was the authority for all local government units to adopt home rule charters for their governance. A sub theme as Thornburgh and other reformers saw it was the opportunity to streamline the governmental process. There was then and over subsequent years continued resistance to the changes a home rule charter would promote and any reform that threatened existing political power structures. Not only is there much material from the drafting sub-committee and home rule committees at the convention but also considerable material following the convention regarding the promotion of home rule for Pittsburgh into the 1970s. Thornburgh in fact was Chair of a Drafting Sub-Committee of the Pittsburgh Home Rule Committee in 1969. Included, too, are speeches, event files and news releases by Thornburgh during 1967-68 and a paper with drafts which he wrote and distributed in 1969 entitled "Blueprint for Modern Government: A Home Rule Charter for Pittsburgh." It is interesting to note that it was not until 1998 that Pittsburgh finally passed its home rule charter. These home rule files are unique in identifying the history of this topic in Pittsburgh over subsequent years as well as during the active period of the convention.
    - Advisory Subcommittee and Drafting Subcommittee
      - Home Rule Advisory Committee and Drafting Sub-Committee, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Clippings regarding formation of Advisory Committee and Drafting Sub-Committee, early 1969 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Richard L. Thornburgh, Chair, Drafting Sub-Committee, early 1969 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - Report of Drafting Sub-Committee of Pittsburgh Home Rule Committee, June 6, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Background Information for report on Drafting Sub-Committee, March 18, 1969 - May 7, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - "County Government under PA Constitution," by PA Economy League, December, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Speeches and Events
      - Speeches, October-November, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Events regarding Home Rule, 1971-1974 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - News Releases
      - Press Releases, 1968-1972 (Box 29, Folder 9)
        - Thornburgh joins as co-sponsor of the proposal of the City of Pittsburgh aimed at providing its citizens with advantages of home rule, control of structure of government and personnel practices, and fiscal tools necessary to govern in years ahead, January 3, 1968
        - Thornburgh hits Home Rule Charter "Footdragging", January, 1969
        - Thornburgh states that home rule is in trouble in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, September 28, 1972
        - Statement for Hearings of Government Study Commission City of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, October 10, 1973
        - Thornburgh tells League of Women Voters of Mt. Lebanon that official inaction on home rule short-changes the people of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, January 12, 1972
    - Correspondence, Notes, Remarks and Drafts
      - Correspondence related to "Blueprint for a Modern Government:..." and January 16, 1969 article from "Point" (Box 29, Folder 10)
      - Paper: "Blueprint for Modern Government: A Home Rule Charter for Pittsburgh" by Thornburgh (with drafts), January 10, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 11)
      - Speech: "Metropolitan Government...Would You Repeat the Question?" as published in Legal Journal vol. 119 No. 3, 3/1/71, March 1, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence to Thornburgh- post draft:, June, 1969-1974 (Box 29, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence and notes of Thornburgh, 1968-1972 (Box 29, Folder 14)
      - Remarks, articles and reports by local and national officials and Thornburgh, 1970-1972 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Home Rule Charter for Pittsburgh and Allegheny County
      - Home Rule Charter- Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Discussion Drafts, 1973-1974 (Box 29, Folder 16)
      - Studies and Reports, 1972-1977 (Box 29, Folder 17)
      - Presentation to Allegheny County Government Study Commission by Committee for Progress in Allegheny County, 1977 (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Pamphlets, Reports and Editorials
      - Home Rule Editorials, 1970-1974 (Box 29, Folder 19)
      - League of Women Voters Home Rule Fact Sheet and Information, 1970-1974 (Box 29, Folder 20)
      - "Local Government Reform in Allegheny County: Can LEAA Help It Happen?" by James M. Seif under Local Government Seminar, University of Pittsburgh, December 1970 (Box 29, Folder 21)
      - Pamphlets and Reports on Home Rule: Local and National Articles on Home Rule, 1965-1969 (Box 29, Folder 22)